<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>self-improvement | Ashwin Narayan</title>
    <link>https://www.ashwinnarayan.com/tag/self-improvement/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://www.ashwinnarayan.com/tag/self-improvement/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>self-improvement</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2020 Ashwin Narayan</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 03 Dec 2020 10:45:29 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://www.ashwinnarayan.com/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>self-improvement</title>
      <link>https://www.ashwinnarayan.com/tag/self-improvement/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Digital Minimalism</title>
      <link>https://www.ashwinnarayan.com/post/digital-minimalism/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Dec 2020 10:45:29 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.ashwinnarayan.com/post/digital-minimalism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;about-the-book&#34;&gt;About the Book&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a heavy user of computer technology for over a decade, I&amp;rsquo;ll be the first defend its benefits. My familiarity with the internet is responsible for a significant chunk of my knowledge and much of my critical thinking abilities. Through personalities like Carl Sagan and Michael Shermer, it also played a big part in me developing an intense interest in science and eventually pursuing a career in it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When something is so useful, you tend to be slow to notice its downsides. In 2016, I started to feel that my technology use was filling large chunks of my time with un-productive habits, preventing me from doing many of the cool things that the internet told me was possible. I often found myself 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.washingtonpost.com/lifestyle/wellness/coronavirus-doom-scrolling-stop/2020/07/29/2c87e9b2-d034-11ea-8d32-1ebf4e9d8e0d_story.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;doom scrolling&lt;/a&gt; on websites like Facebook, Instagram or reddit at the end of my workday and during weekends. My habit of mindless browsing was taking away time that I could be putting into developing new skills that I wanted to develop. In other words, I was starting to feel like I was losing control over my time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found Digital Minimalism when I was searching for methods that would help me stay on task when I was using tech. The book contains very practical advice on how to change habits surrounding technology usage and halped me free up large chunks of my time for pursuits that I find more satisfying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re the kind of person that finds themselves deep in a reddit thread about annoying habits of co-workers ten minutes after opening up your laptop for responding to an email, this book might help. For me, the most useful feature of the book is how it builds a coherent theory of how humans interact with technology. Newport takes many different negative aspects of unstructured technology use, and brings it together under one theoretical framework and uses this framework to dispense specific advice about how to make things better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;humans-are-biologically-wired-in-certain-ways&#34;&gt;Humans are Biologically Wired in Certain Ways&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mentions three key things that human brains have evolved to find satisfaction in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Real-World Social Interactions:&lt;/strong&gt; Interacting with people in the real world involves processing a dense, &amp;ldquo;high-bandwidth&amp;rdquo; stream of information that engages multiple senses. Newport suggests that as a social species, humans have evolved to find satisfaction in such high-bandwidth social interactions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Occasional Solitude:&lt;/strong&gt; Newport cites scientific studies to build the case that the brain does important types of reflective thinking when you are alone and that this might be very important to develop as a person. He also gives some case studies of famous people who have found value in developing new ideas for their work in solitude.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Building Physical Things:&lt;/strong&gt; As a species that evolved to use tools, Newport argues that humans are wired to find satisfaction in seeing physical consequences of our efforts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;modern-tech-optimizes-for-capturing-and-holding-human-attention&#34;&gt;Modern Tech Optimizes for Capturing and Holding Human Attention&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book highlights the fact that many technologies such as mobile apps and social media websites are precisely engineered to capture and maintain as much of our attention as possible. Since the users&amp;rsquo; attention is the source of revenue for many apps and websites, it is natural for them to optimize themselves for how much attention they can capture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Social Interactions:&lt;/strong&gt; Social media captures your attention by providing social approval (which the brain craves) but through low bandwidth channels such as &amp;ldquo;likes&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;upvotes&amp;rdquo;. The book argues that these signals of social approval keep our brains engaged in the app, leaving us with less time for real social interactions but leave us dissatisified because of their low bandwidth nature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Solitude:&lt;/strong&gt; Constantly being &amp;ldquo;plugged-in&amp;rdquo; into these apps and websites prevents our brains from getting solitude from time to time, depriving it of time to reflect. This could have negative effects such as increasing anxiety and less time for developing creative ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Physical Hobbies:&lt;/strong&gt; Time spent using tech also necessarily means less time for developing hobbies that involve building physical things. Newport argues that activities like programming or building websites don&amp;rsquo;t quite satisfy our brains in the same way as building a fence or a house.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-books-recommendation&#34;&gt;The Book&amp;rsquo;s Recommendation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To mitigate these negative affects of technology, the book recommends adopting a philosophy of technology use that guides which technologies to adopt and which to avoid. This requires first getting a good idea of your values and goals in life and only adopting the use of technologies that align with your values and goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book warns that one-off hacks like switching to a smart-phone or blocking time-wasting websites won&amp;rsquo;t work on their own without an over-arching philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;digital-minimalism&#34;&gt;Digital Minimalism&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cal Newport&amp;rsquo;s calls his preferred philosophy of technology use &lt;strong&gt;Digital Minimalism&lt;/strong&gt;. Digital minimalism starts with a one month technology detox during which you cut out all non-essential technology from your life. The month is used to evaluate whether any of the tech you used to use actually aligned with your goals and values.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;recommended-values&#34;&gt;Recommended Values&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book also goes one step further and uses what science knows about human nature to recommend some specific values that may be useful to adopt when dealing with technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prioritize Real-World Social Interaction:&lt;/strong&gt; Use technology to increase the amount of time that you spend on face-to-face interactions with people.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Schedule Solitude:&lt;/strong&gt; Use the time that may be gained from cutting out distracting tech, spend more time on your own and let your brain get a healthy amount of time to reflect quietly on things.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Physical Hobbies:&lt;/strong&gt; Consider adopting hobbies that involve creating and shaping material with the hands.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;verify-before-trusting&#34;&gt;Verify Before Trusting&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the source of income for much of the tech that we use is our attention, it will naturally optimize for capturing and holding our attention for as long as possible even if it is not in our interest. So the book recommends treating all new tech first with suspcion and letting the tech into our lives only after we have determined that it aligns with our goals and values. Periodically evaluating tech that you&amp;rsquo;ve already let in to make sure that its behaviour has not changed may also be a good idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;closing-thoughts&#34;&gt;Closing Thoughts&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that the book gets right the idea that we need a philosophy of technology use so that it does not prevent us from achieving our goals. However, I think that some of the recommended values may be specific to the author. In particular, I find that writing code or making PCBs often scratch my creative itch just fine. In fact, I have an aversion to sports or things that make me feel physically winded or sweaty. I think that the most valuable takeaway from the book is that it&amp;rsquo;s a good idea to make sure that the technology and tools that you use align with your values and goals. What those values and goals should be is up to you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On the Effective Use of TODO Lists</title>
      <link>https://www.ashwinnarayan.com/post/what-i-learned-about-todo-lists/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 May 2020 13:30:50 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.ashwinnarayan.com/post/what-i-learned-about-todo-lists/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like many countries around the world, Singapore entered a lockdown (a &amp;ldquo;circuit-breaker&amp;rdquo; to use the local terminology) on April 4 to stem the rapid spread of COVID-19. Knowing how easy it is to get distracted from work and lose productivity at home, I made a commitment to myself at the start of the lockdown to use the extra time to improve myself. Specifically I wanted to improve my workflows for many of my daily tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A key part of the effort is my renewed commitment to TODO lists. I&amp;rsquo;ve made several attempts to integrate TODO lists as a habit into my life before, but the habit has never stuck. As a result, I use TODO lists quite loosely - &lt;em&gt;i.e.&lt;/em&gt; when things get super hectic and I have no choice but to use them to keep me sane. Otherwise, I simply remember the big picture of what I want to get done. While this has led to me forgetting to do the odd task, I felt that my overall productivity was not significantly impacted. If I really want to remember something, I might stick a Post-It note on my work desk. However, I decided recently that this was not good enough for me for two reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I want to improve myself as a person.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I want to take on more responsibilities and work and this is only possible if I improve this part of myself.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So about a week into the lockdown, I decided to use TODO lists to track all my tasks for the next 30 days. If I saw real improvements in these 30 days, I&amp;rsquo;d keep the system. If not, I&amp;rsquo;d try to find a better one. I put some weight into the commitment by purchasing for myself a premium account in the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://todoist.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;todoist app&lt;/a&gt;. While the system felt awkward and cumbersome at the start, I began to notice tangible improvements at the two week mark. With a little experimentation, I was able to optimize TODO lists to work for me. Here&amp;rsquo;s what I learned from the 30 day experiment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-believe-in-the-system&#34;&gt;1. Believe in the System&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In all my previous attempts, I started with a lot of skepticism about the effectiveness of using TODO lists. This time, I decided that I was going to proceed as though it was going to work. This seemed to make a big difference in how the experiment worked out. I observed straight away that I was more motivated to find ways to make the system work for me. In the past, I&amp;rsquo;d give up on the method when some small obstacle popped up (the app not having some small feature that I wanted for instance).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;2-use-it-for-everything&#34;&gt;2. Use it for Everything&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read that this is similar to David Allen&amp;rsquo;s advice in his book &amp;ldquo;Getting Things Done&amp;rdquo;. It does help to capture in the list absolutely everything that you want to get done. Doing this meant that I did not need to keep a running list of all my tasks in my brain. I didn’t realize that keeping my task list in my head was generating a low background radiation of anxiety in my brain until I stopped doing it. Capture everything in your task list - both personal and work-related.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;3-use-a-cross-platform-system&#34;&gt;3. Use a Cross-Platform System&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve experimented with systems like the bullet journal before. While I do like the feeling of having a physical notebook to write down tasks in, I found that I became too dependent on the notebook. If I forgot to bring the notebook anywhere (which can happen), I got lost. Using a cross platform task tracking app that works on both the desktop and on the phone is more convenient and ensures that you&amp;rsquo;ll have your task list with you pretty much wherever you go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;4-check-the-list-before-starting-work&#34;&gt;4. Check the List Before Starting Work&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Previously, I&amp;rsquo;d just sit down and start working on whatever floated to the top of my head at that moment. While this works great when you don&amp;rsquo;t have that many things to do, it may result in small things being forgotten and pushed to the last minute. In addition to making me more intentional about what I was doing, checking my list before starting work also made me more likely to finish off more of the small tasks before they accumulated to annoying levels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;5-theres-a-time-and-place-for-specificity&#34;&gt;5. There&amp;rsquo;s a Time and Place for Specificity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a time and place for everything, but not now. &lt;em&gt;-Professor Oak&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most important thing I learned is to choose the right level of specificity when entering tasks into the list. My first instinct was to overdo it. I made full use of the fact that you could nest subtasks pretty deep in todoist (4 levels) and wrote big picture items into the list and started breaking it down into smaller steps. Then I started doing the task and found out that the steps that I wrote down were either too optimistic completely unnecessary. However, when I tried only writing down the big picture tasks, they became too big and scary and I didn’t want to touch them. In the end what worked for me was to write down only big picture things when I first enter the task into the system. When I start working on the task, I click into it and start adding sub-tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another thing I learned about &amp;ldquo;sub-tasking&amp;rdquo; was not to add sub-tasks too far into the future. The further ahead I planned the more my plan deviated from reality and the more I had to delete what I wrote and replan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;6--choose-the-right-level-of-specificity&#34;&gt;6.  Choose the Right Level of Specificity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a related note to point 5, I recommend experimenting a bit to find the right level of task specificity for the subtasks. I experimented with breaking up large tasks into subtasks that took from 1 minute all the way up to a few hours. I found subtasks that took between 5 and 15 minutes to be the most rewarding. Anything smaller added too much overhead to the tasks. Anything longer exponentially decreased the probability that I’d start working on that task.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Choosing a consistent level of specificity also solved the problem of unequal weighting of tasks for me. Checking off tasks is actually quite rewarding on its own. When the reward for checking off one big task that took 5 hours to do was the same as the reward for a two minute task, it gave me less motivation to tackle the big tasks. Once I started choosing a consistent level of specificity for the tasks that I checked off, larger tasks became naturally more rewarding than the smaller tasks and my productivity on larger tasks improved as a result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;7-consider-gamification&#34;&gt;7. Consider Gamification&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s some evidence that gamification of tasks can help improve the motivation for completing them. I don’t think that gamification can work as a base motivation but it may help a little with the day to day motivation. For me, the simple points system on todoist adds a small touch of motivation without adding too much overhead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;8-attach-it-to-your-bedtime-routine&#34;&gt;8. Attach it to Your Bedtime Routine&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Checking the list one last time before turning in is really helpful. It feels good to clear the schedule for the day and have a sense of resolution. I recommend doing this even if you haven&amp;rsquo;t finished everything on the list. Simply reschedule the unfinished items to the next day but get to zero tasks remaining for the day. Integrating it into my bedtime routine has also helped with my effort to avoid browsing the phone mindlessly in bed before going to sleep. I set a simple rule for myself: Once I clear the day&amp;rsquo;s list, I can&amp;rsquo;t use the phone anymore and must go to sleep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;9-dont-let-perfect-be-the-enemy-of-good&#34;&gt;9. Don&amp;rsquo;t Let Perfect be the Enemy of Good&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is related to me giving up on systems too early. I realized that I tend to try and find the perfect process to do things before even trying. While this is useful in many situations, it has sometimes led to me not doing things in the first place. If you have a proclivity for perfection, don&amp;rsquo;t let it get in the way of you trying new but imperfect systems. Just remember that you can always optimize later. The more important thing is to get started.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
