<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Ashwin Narayan</title>
    <link>https://www.ashwinnarayan.com/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Ashwin Narayan</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2019 Ashwin Narayan</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://www.ashwinnarayan.com/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Cartpole Dynamics and Control</title>
      <link>https://www.ashwinnarayan.com/post/cartpole-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Apr 2019 15:56:44 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.ashwinnarayan.com/post/cartpole-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>Introduction As is the case for a lot of PhDs, my main work focuses on a small part of robotics. There are many areas of robotics that I would love to work on but do not. As part of my ongoing effort to learn more about these areas, I work on accessible problems that interest me. One area of robotics that fascinates me is that of rigid body dynamics and control.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning Haskell Through Google Code Jam</title>
      <link>https://www.ashwinnarayan.com/post/learning-haskell-google-code-jam/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Apr 2019 08:26:34 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.ashwinnarayan.com/post/learning-haskell-google-code-jam/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Over the last year or so, I&amp;rsquo;ve been playing around with functional programming. As the first few lines of the Wikipedia page suggest, functional programming is all about expressing a computation or algorithm as the composition of functions rather than using a state that changes over time. From what I&amp;rsquo;ve understood so far, functional programming is based on lambda calculus which is an alternative but equivalent formulation of the famous Turing Machine that most modern computers are based on.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Witcher 3: Wild Hunt - A Review</title>
      <link>https://www.ashwinnarayan.com/post/witcher-3-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Sep 2018 01:10:46 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.ashwinnarayan.com/post/witcher-3-review/</guid>
      <description>The Witcher 3 follows the story of Geralt of Rivia, a Witcher or monster slayer in search of his adoptive daugter Cirllia. (well it&amp;rsquo;s not his story but we see the story through his eyes!). Set in a medieval world - after an event called the conjunction of spheres - magic and monsters (werewolves, spectres, vampire and the like.) roam the world. Witchers are magically and genetically enhanced humans that were created intentionally by sorcerers to help fight off these monsters.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hugo Web Development Workflow on Windows</title>
      <link>https://www.ashwinnarayan.com/post/hugo-windows-workflow/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Dec 2017 11:41:31 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.ashwinnarayan.com/post/hugo-windows-workflow/</guid>
      <description>As I mentioned in my first article on this blog, I&amp;rsquo;m now using Hugo, the static site generator to build my personal website. Due to the needs of my work environment (mostly because I need to use MS Word and certain MATLAB features on a regular basis), I&amp;rsquo;ve been primarily using Windows as my operating system for the past year or so. Having used Linux for a long time, I definitely missed the conveniences offered by shell scripting and other command line tools.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Review of Star Trek: Discovery</title>
      <link>https://www.ashwinnarayan.com/post/star-trek-discovery/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Dec 2017 23:26:48 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.ashwinnarayan.com/post/star-trek-discovery/</guid>
      <description>This article contains spoilers for all the episodes of Star Trek: Discovery.
As a lover of good science fiction I was really happy to hear the announcement of Star Trek: Discovery. I have not watched all of old Star Trek. But from the few that I have watched (Mostly Star Trek: Then Next Generation), I have come to love the Trek universe and the way it handles science fiction.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Integrate Quaternions</title>
      <link>https://www.ashwinnarayan.com/post/how-to-integrate-quaternions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Sep 2017 17:58:08 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.ashwinnarayan.com/post/how-to-integrate-quaternions/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been spending a lot of time working with inertial measurement units recently and am discovering the surprising amount of mathematics that goes into using data from accelerometers and gyroscopes to get the orientation of an object in 3D space. The story begins with me trying to integrate an angular velocity vector (in 3D) to get the orientation of an object. Angular velocity is a vector but common representations of orientation (like Euler Angles) are not.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bash Recipes for Doing Science!</title>
      <link>https://www.ashwinnarayan.com/post/bash-recipes-for-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Aug 2017 19:30:14 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.ashwinnarayan.com/post/bash-recipes-for-science/</guid>
      <description>When prototyping programs that deal with lots of data on an Arduino and other embedded systems or even on full blown computers, it&amp;rsquo;s really useful to have a quick tool for plotting the output of the program. Initially, I used python for doing this. Python is a beautifully simple language and between Numpy, Scipy and Matplotlib, you can do pretty much anything you want with data; from doing simple plotting to running machine learning algorithms on the data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Programming Complex Dataflows in C</title>
      <link>https://www.ashwinnarayan.com/post/dataflow-programming-in-c/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Aug 2017 00:15:14 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.ashwinnarayan.com/post/dataflow-programming-in-c/</guid>
      <description>Over the past few months I&amp;rsquo;ve been spending a lot of time on implementing various signal processing algorithms in C/C++. Things like Kalman Filters, various types of FIR filters and finite state machines. The number of steps needed to implement each these algorithms were fairly small and in the beginning I tried to put all the functionality of these implementations into simple to use C++ classes. This made things look neater and also fit in quite well with the Arduino programming framework (I was implementing a lot of these algorithms on Arduino compatible microcontrollers like the Teensy).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ICRA 2017</title>
      <link>https://www.ashwinnarayan.com/post/icra-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jun 2017 22:50:52 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.ashwinnarayan.com/post/icra-2017/</guid>
      <description>The IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA) that happened in Singapore over the last week is often referred to as the robotics conference. If you&amp;rsquo;re an academic working in the field of robotics, Singapore was the place to be in the last week. So I spent most of my time hanging around the Marina Bay Sands Hotel Convention center as a student volunteer for the conference, helping out and - in my free time - attending some of the hundreds of presentations that that took place.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Real-Time Programming with Xenomai 3 - Part 2: Writing a simple periodic task.</title>
      <link>https://www.ashwinnarayan.com/post/xenomai-realtime-programming-part-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 May 2017 23:10:16 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.ashwinnarayan.com/post/xenomai-realtime-programming-part-2/</guid>
      <description>Xenomai gets tasks to run in real-time by having a co-kernel running alongside the regular linux kernel handling all the time critical tasks. The Xenomai co-kernel is able to do this because of the i-pipe patch that the custom kernel is compiled with. This patch adds an interrupt pipeline that sits between the hardware of the computer and any kernels running on the hardware. The interrupt pipeline has domains which can be assigned a priority.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Real-Time Programming with Xenomai 3 - Part 1: Installation and Basic Setup</title>
      <link>https://www.ashwinnarayan.com/post/xenomai-realtime-programming/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 May 2017 00:07:36 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.ashwinnarayan.com/post/xenomai-realtime-programming/</guid>
      <description>In my lab, we recently started moving away from Simulink&amp;rsquo;s Real-Time packages and towards Real-Time Linux for implementing the low level control of our robots. I thought I would document what I went through to get Xenomai (A Real-Time framework for linux) working stably as a resource for others trying to get started on the same thing.
What is Real-Time? The word &amp;ldquo;real-time&amp;rdquo; is used in a lot of different fields to mean different things.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Brand New Website!</title>
      <link>https://www.ashwinnarayan.com/post/welcome/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 May 2017 00:38:51 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.ashwinnarayan.com/post/welcome/</guid>
      <description>My old website was formatted a lot like an online resume - something I feel doesn&amp;rsquo;t quite fit me any more after I decided to join a PhD program. So I decided to refresh my website deisgn into something that fit my current research interests. I also wanted a platform where I could blog about my work and personal projects. I&amp;rsquo;ve read blogs by many active researchers and I feel that the informal tone and nature of a blog allows more accessible explanations of research than formal journal/conference papers - where the language can often be very terse and full of jargon.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>